Guide to the Oregon State University Military Photographs Collection 1875-1975
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center
- Pre World War One, 1875-1917; Series I
  - OAC Cadet Battalion - Close Order Column of Companies, circa 1895; P002:384; mounted 8X10 photographic print (Box 10)
    Mounted Print, titled, "OAC Cadet Battalion - May 1895 - Close Order Column of Companies". The uniforms are consistent with the 1890 period, showing the Forage Caps and sack coat patterns in blue. Formation of cadets with the Cadet Band on parade field appears to be an inspection event, with seated observers under tree in background. The print is stamped on reverse with "Ore. State University Archives". There is a handwritten note included in sleeve stating "Found in (with title page) 1893-4 Catalog". This would put the dating of this photograph in question based on the caption written on the front. The period uniforms and Benton Hall configuration are consistent with a circa date of 1895.
  - OAC Cadets drilling with rifles overheads - Benton Hall in background, circa 1907; P002:386; 8X10 photographic print (Box 1)
    Print 8x10. OAC Cadets drilling on field on lower campus. Benton hall in background, water tank and smokestack of power plant (now Owens hall) behind. Good detail of Education Hall to the left of photo. Men are drilling with rifles held overhead, lead by Cadet officer with sabre.
  - OAC Cadet formation with Benton Hall, circa 1895; P002:389; 8X10 photographic print (Box 1)
    Cadets in review in front of Benton Hall. Uniforms date prior to 1900, probably a similar circa 1895 formation photo. Longer rifled muskets of 1880s vintage. Uniforms include the older "forage cap" still in use dating to Civil War.
  - OAC Cadet officers portrait with backdrop circa 1900 #2, P002:400; 7X9 photographic print (Box 1)
    Posed photograph in front of backdrop of OAC Officer Cadets. Identification of subjects based on "Alumni Files", with dating of 1898-1902 and a received date of 1960. The uniforms are of the circa 1900 vintage, including high collars and older style campaign hats. The identification of subjects written in pen on reverse has been edited in red pencil. "Standing 1- (Blank), 2- Dr. Berges, 3. John Edwards 1902 class, 4 - (Blank), Sitting: 1- Alfred Saunders (Jake), 2- Grant Elgin. Note written later: #3, Standing, also identified as Major Frank Edwards, Dec. 1914."
  - OAC Cadet band, formation circa 1900, P002:424; 2.0 prints 2 Cyannotype prints with 2 8x10 b/w reprints of originals; 8X10 photographic print (Box 1)
    Contemporary prints of early Cyannotype prints (2 each). OAC band in formation with instruments. Uniforms date to turn of the century with brimmed caps and blue tunics. Circa 1900 written on reverse.
  - Cyannotype print cadet formation lower campus, circa 1905; P002:425; 6X8 photographic print (Box 1)
    Cyannotype print. Formation of OAC Cadets with rifles on lower campus with Benton Hall in background circa 1895. Paleontology Bldg (Built 1892, now Woman's center) to the right of Benton Hall. Men are wearing the standard blue tunics with brimmed caps. Rifles show the older type of bayonets, probably on Rifles of Pre Spanish American war vintage.
  - Portrait of cadet officers, circa 1895; P002:426; 8x10 cyannotype print, 2 4x5 b/w prints and 4x5 negative (Box 1)
    Cadet officers posing with sabres. Tunics have the large chevrons on sleeves denoting cadets rank. Previous description states "Booklet OAC Cadets 1908-09" this dating is probably incorrect. This photo is posed at the base of Benton Hall (then Administration Bldg) steps and the facade is still in original brick. Renovations in 1899 covered brick with stucco. Photo is probably dated circa 1895. Uniforms are vintage with brimmed caps with OAC badge. Officer's uniform shows rank on shoulderboads.
  - Portrait of Cadet Officers, circa 1895; P002:426; mounted 8X10 photographic print (Box 10)
    Posed photograph of cadet officers with the military commander below steps of Benton Hall. Uniforms of the mid 1890s vintage with forage caps and OAC badges. Photograph is probably a larger print of one published in the OAC Catalog. Good detail of the old brick facade of Benton Hall prior to the 1899 renovations.
  - Cadet formation - grey uniforms with rifles, circa 1880; P002:427; mounted 8X10 photographic print (Box 10)
    Formation of OAC Cadets wearing the Pre 1893 Grey uniforms with civil war era forage caps. The uniforms of this period were of a Civil War vintage style, Grey in color based on the allegiance of the College President. Unknown date of photograph, mid 1880s is a good possibility based on the string of boxcars in background with the curved logo of the Corvallis and Eastern Railroad. Significant early photograph of OAC Cadet Corps.
  - OAC Cadet Company photo, circa 1905; P002:445; 8X10 photographic print (Box 10)
    Cadet company photograph, probably circa 1905. Cadets in standard uniforms with brimmed forage caps. Rifles appear to be the Krag Jorgensen type. The condition of the mount shows some staining and tears of mounting board. Photo is probably a larger print of a published photo in Beaver Yearbook.
  - OAC Cadets on parade in Portland to honor Teddy Roosevelt, circa 1912; P002:553; 1.0 photographic print; 5X7 photographic print (Box 1)
    OAC Cadet battalion marching in parade to honor Theodore Roosevelt in Portland Oregon. Good detail of city streets. Cadets are marching with rifles. Campaign hats are worn with uniforms.
  - Formation of OAC Cadets on lower campus, circa 1910; P002:568; 8X20 panoramic print (Box 11)
    Formation of a cadet company in review. Possibly a photograph used in OAC publication such as Orange Yearbook or Oregon Stater. Uniforms are of the 1902-1908 pattern including canvas leggings and 1902 brimmed service caps. Uniforms of this type were transitional between the old blue style and the change to WWI khaki.
  - Real Photo Postcard, Inspection Co. I, 1910, P002:569; 3.5X5.5 photographic postcard (Box 1)
    Real Photo Postcard, postmark Aug 1, 1910, One Cent stamp. Photo of inspection of cadet troops on lower campus with Education building in background. Cadets are wearing Pre WWI brimmed caps and canvas leggings. Rifles being inspected in back row have fixed bayonets. Notation in bottom right corner is Inspection Co. I '10. Reverse of card is addressed to Miss Esther Graham, Newport Oregon.
  - Column Right, March!, Cadets in formation, circa 1915; P002:585; 3.5X5.5 photographic print (Box 1)
    Cadet column marching on lower campus with onlookers. The uniforms of the cadets indicate Pre WWI era. This is supported by the two women's clothes watching the formation pass. 2 copies of photograph, original is stamped with E.T. Reed, College Editor, Oregon Agricultural College, Corvallis Oregon. There is a postage stamp style sticker also for the Hicks Chatten Co. Photo Engravers, Portland Oregon.
  - Real Photo Postcard Cadet Regiment with Benton Hall, circa 1915; P002:590; 3.0 photographs; 3.5X5.5 photographic postcard (Box 1)
    Cadets in formation on lower field below Benton Hall. Real Photo Postcard. Based on the leggings and service caps, uniforms could be Pre WWI (era 1912-17) Dating information based on the Post Card is AZO w/4 corner triangles, dating to 1904-1918. Detail of formation shows a full regimental inspection, with entire cadet corps in attendance. This photo shows units on the lower field with Benton Hall in background.
  - Cadet regiment forming up for review Benton Hall lower campus, circa 1915; P002:627; 3.5X5.5 photographic print (Box 1)
    Cadets marching into formation on lower field below Benton Hall. Related to P002:628 with completed regimental formation. Based on the leggings and service caps, uniforms could be Pre WWI (era 1912-17) Real Photo Postcard P002:590 is the final result of this cadet assembly. Dating information based on the Post Card is AZO w/4 corner triangles, dating to 1904-1918. Detail of formation shows a full regimental inspection, with entire cadet corps in attendance. This photo shows units marching into the field from the rear, forming up on the lower field with Benton Hall in background.
  - Cadet Regiment inspection formation below Benton Hall, circa 1915; P002:628; 1.0 3 x 5 prints; 3.5X5.5 photographic print (Box 1)
    Cadets marching into formation on lower field below Benton Hall. Related to P002:628 with completed regimental formation. Based on the leggings and service caps, uniforms could be Pre WWI (era 1912-17) Real Photo Postcard P002:590 is the final result of this cadet assembly. Dating information based on the Post Card is AZO w/4 corner triangles, dating to 1904-1918. Detail of formation shows a full regimental inspection, with entire cadet corps in attendance. This photo shows units forming up on the lower field with Benton Hall in background.
  - OAC Cadet officer studio portrait circa 1900, P002:697; 5X10 photographic print (Box 1)
    Posed photo of OAC Cadet officer in portrait studio photograph. Posed with sabre in dress tunic. Rank epaulets of the circa 1900 era uniform. Cadet has OAC collar badges and early style campaign hat. Photograph is mounted in oval format with decoration around edge. Portrait was done at the Gardner Photography Studio in Corvallis, Oregon. This period print was probably made for OAC publication.
  - OAC Cadets with caisson/limbers Benton Hall in background, circa 1905; P002:698; 5.5X6.5 photographic print (Box 1)
    Cadet formation on lower campus showing 2 caisson/limbers. Uniforms of the 1900-1909 period with high collars of white shirts, early style campaign hats and shoulder epaulette rank insignias. Benton hall in background has been converted to stucco from the original brick, dating to later than 1899. Early style caissons are for ceremonial purposes/training with horse teams and not set up for artillery.
  - Cadet company formation Mechanical Hall in background., circa 1905; P002:699; 5X11.5 photographic print (Box 1)
    Smaller version of panoramic style photograph. Cadet regiment formation in dress uniforms and rifles, forage caps and high collar tunics, circa 1900-1909. Newly built Mechanical Hall in background. Smoke stack of plant now in Owen Hall behind Mechanical Hall building. Caption written in fountain pen: "OAC Cadets '05" Photograph can be attributed to Emery Photographers.
  - Cyannotype print Cadets and 3 girls under tree, circa 1885; P002:700; 5X8 photographic print (Box 1)
    Two cadets in old style grey uniform under a tree with 3 young ladies. This style of grey uniform was in use up to 1892. Large chevron rank stripes on shoulders. Pencil notation on reverse: "1-15-62 Clyde Phillips states grey uniform worn until 1892 only Before 1900" Print is probably not of the 1885 vintage and was done at a later date.
  - Right Shoulder Arms, cadet company, circa 1900; P002:701; 7X9 photographic print (Box 1)
    Cadet formation with rifles at right shoulder arms with fixed bayonets. Uniforms of the turn of the century vintage with early style campaign hats. Rifles show the older type of bayonets, probably the Trapdoor Rifles of Pre Spanish American war vintage.
  - Cadet formation fixed bayonets, circa 1912; P002:702; 5X7 photographic print (Box 1)
    Mounted print of Cadet company with fixed bayonets. Brimmed service caps of the 1911 pattern with canvas leggings date the uniforms to between 1910-1915. The rifles issued are the M1898 Krag-Jorgensen bolt action of the Spanish American War vintage, they were the first rifles to mount a modern style knife bayonet. Very clear and detailed picture of weapons and uniforms.
  - Cadet company formation, circa 1910; P002:703; 7X9 photographic print (Box 1)
    Mounted print of cadet formation in dress uniforms/white gloves. At attention in review. Uniforms indicate c1910 with brimmed caps and canvas leggings. A poor quality print, showing some silvering at edges.
  - Staff of Regimental Corps of Cadets, OAC, circa 1915, P002:704; 5X9.5 photographic print (Box 1)
    Staff officers and NCOs of the Regimental Corps of Cadets, Oregon Agricultural College. Probably before WWI, but after 1911 when the Armory was constructed. Seated in the center of the front row appears to be Colonel U.G. Mc Alexander, probably during his 1915-1916 period at OAC. Officers are seated in the front row, holding sabres, uniforms are of Pre WWI vintage with brimmed caps. The leather leggings were usually worn by officers. Photo is stamped on reverse with "Return to Room 222 Agricultural Hall, OAC Corvallis, ORE" and has a Barometer photo stamp, date to run 6/2 (with no year listed)
  - Company Portrait, OAC Cadets with rifles, circa 1915; P002:706; 9X12 photographic print (Box 1)
    Company portrait for yearbook. Infantry company of OAC cadets posing for yearly photo. Men are holding the M1898 Krag-Jorgensen rifle (Spanish American War vintage). The uniforms are indicative of the Pre WWI era with brimmed service caps and canvas leggings. High collars are starting to show badges of specialty and OAC emblems. The two cadet officers seated at center of first row have the cavalry style leather leggings and ceremonial sabres. Clear photograph, possibly published in OAC yearbook.
  - Military review of cadets in formation, circa 1915; P002:803; 3.5X5.5 photographic print (Box 1)
    Inspection of cadets in formation by cadet officers and Military officer. Leggings and service caps indicate a pre-WWI uniform style. Rifles are M1896 Krag-Jorgensen bolt action of Spanish American War vintage. Dating of circa 1915 is based on early style brim on service caps and canvas leggings. The inspection day by the Military Department was a special event each year on the OAC Campus
  - OAC Cadet officer and NCO walking by Education Building, circa 1915; P002:804; 3.5X5.5 photographic print (Box 1)
    Cadet officer with striped on sleeve of dress uniform walking with Army NCO assigned to OAC (both with great moustaches!) walking on pathway near Education Hall (then Science Building) Dating of circa 1915 is based on early style brim on service caps and canvas leggings. The inspection day by the Military Department was a special event each year on the OAC Campus
  - Two officers with sabres, Education hall in background, circa 1915; P002:805; 3.5X5.5 photographic print (Box 1)
    Two Army officers walking with Education Hall in background. Uniform styles show the use of the dress blue tunic with covered buttons and high collars on one officer. Rank insignia on shoulder boards. Dating of circa 1915 is based on early style brim on service caps and leggings. The inspection day by the Military Department was a special event each year on the OAC Campus
  - Informal group of officers on Inspection Day, circa 1915; P002:806; 3.5X5.5 photographic print (Box 1)
    Informal group of officers conversing on parade field, probably inspection day. Dress uniforms with Blue tunics and yellow stripes on trousers are of the pre-WWI vintage. Service caps indicate a pre-WWI uniform style as well. Rifles are M1896 Krag-Jorgensen bolt action of Spanish American War vintage. Dating of circa 1915 is based on early style brim on service caps and canvas leggings. The inspection day by the Military Department was a special event each year on the OAC Campus
  - Officers with unidentified dignitary, circa 1915; P002:807; 3.5X5.5 photographic print (Box 1)
    Informal group of officers conversing on parade field, probably inspection day. Unidentified dignitary in overcoat and bowler hat may be Military Department representative. Dress uniforms with Blue tunics and yellow stripes on trousers are of the pre-WWI vintage. Service caps indicate a pre-WWI uniform style as well. Rifles are M1896 Krag-Jorgensen bolt action of Spanish American War vintage. Dating of circa 1915 is based on early style brim on service caps and canvas leggings. The inspection day by the Military Department was a special event each year on the OAC Campus
  - Military officer, unidentified, circa 1890; P002:819; 7X9 photographic print (Box 10)
    Unidentified officer, wearing high collar tunic and overcoat with collar turned up. Rank insignia shows 2 vertical bars and 3 six pointed stars embroidered. Picture appears to be a published photo from book or lithographed print. Unknown origin, some foxing on edges with pin holes in corners.
  - Large portrait of Capt. Woodbridge Geary, circa 1898; P002:821; 16X20 photographic print (Box 12)
    Mounted print (lithograph ?). Large portrait of Captain Woodbridge Geary, an Oregon Native who was killed in the Philippine Insurrection of 1899. The Army named a coastal gun battery on Corregidor Island after this war hero. Large portrait is done by E. W. Moore, no date. The List of Army Officers from 1779-1900 lists Geary with the following entry:
    Geary, Woodbridge (Born in Ore. Appointed from Ore.) addl. 2nd Lieut of 19th Inf., 13 June 1882. 1st Lieut. 19th Inf., 20 Feb 1891., Capt. of Inf., 30 June 1898, Ass'd to 13th Inf., 1 Jan 1899. Died of wounds received in action in Philippine Islands, 11 Oct 1899. Reference file in Memorabilia Collection (MC) on Geary, with transcripts of OAC Barometer articles.
  - Group photo of OAC Spanish American War Veterans, circa 1900; P002:822; 35X25 photographic print (Box 15)
    Print mounted on canvas. Period photograph of OAC's Spanish American War veterans, posed group of 34 men in period uniforms, c.1900. The June 1900 Barometer states that "At the outbreak of the late Spanish War, 48 of the cadets and graduates of the college shouldered the rifle to fight for the flag, and the then Commandant, Capt. Woodbridge Geary, and three of the students gave up their lives on their country's altar". Publication of the photograph is included in the Military section of the June 1900 Barometer. The June issues acted as sort of a yearbook prior to the beginning of "the Orange". Photograph is in poor condition, as transferred from the Horning Museum Collection in August 1996, with damage to the right side. Soldiers are all in period field uniforms, various unit badges are seen on the standard campaign hats. Description of item includes one identification of Harvey L. McAlister ("Pap Hayseed"). Photo does appear to be taken here in the United States, possibly Oregon, ivy and background vegetation does not appear to be tropical. Significant OAC artifact.
- World War One, 1916-1918; Series II
  Photographs in this series are dated from 1916, before the U.S. entry into the war. Uniforms and training reflected the world wide conflict and are indicated in the photographs. SATC (Student Army Training Corps) and early ROTC cadets are featured. Navy ROTC had a presence on the OAC Campus during WWI and did not return until after WWII.
  - WWI to early 1920s Glass Negatives, 1917-1920
    Sub-series contains glass negatives and positives of OAC cadets during WWI and post era (early 1920s) Series contains stock photographs found in OAC publications of the period. Photos include Cadets leaving for US Army service (1918) and training scenes taken just after WWI for use in promoting OAC ROTC Cadet program.
    - General U.G. Mc Alexander in dress uniform, circa 1919; P002:362; 11X14 glass negative (Box 5)
      Oversize glass negative. General McAlexander in dress uniform with medals. Negative version often seen prints of the "Rock of the Marne".
    - 1st OAC Training Detachment ready to leave for WWI, 1918, August 10, 1918; P002:368; 8X10 glass positive (Box 6)
      First OAC Training Detachment in formation ready to leave for WWI, August 10, 1918. Ball Studio photograph. Formation of cadets wearing standard US Army uniforms of WWI. Campaign Hats issued with early style canvas puttees. Rifles are Krag-Jorgensen .30 cal. bolt action. Benton Hall and old bandstand in background.
    - Cadets training with rifles in field, circa 1918; P002:369; 8X10 glass positive (Box 6)
      Line of cadets in prone position with Krag-Jorgensen rifles. Training in rural field, barn and hills in background. Officers in rear giving orders. Uniforms are of WWI vintage including campaign hats and bedrolls over shoulders. Line of prone soldiers probably of company strength. Ball Studio photo.
    - Cadets on training manoeuvres, rural landscape, circa 1918; P002:370; 8X10 glass positive (Box 6)
      Cadets training infantry tactics somewhere in rural Benton County. Panorama view of troops advancing up rolling hills, with cadets in foreground playing dead. Smoke from simulated explosions visible in photograph. Cadets are in full field dress with bedrolls and equipment, WWI uniform styles. Ball Studio photo.
    - SATC Cadet formation on East Quad, circa 1918; P002:394; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      Cadet formation in rain on east quad with Library (now Kidder Hall) and Shepard Hall in background. The SATC program only lasted one year and was replaced with ROTC after WWI. The uniforms are of WWI vintage, with overcoats and campaign hats. Rainy weather indicates fall or winter season. Library building was completed in 1918.
    - Mounted OAC Cavalry cadets, circa 1917; P002:391; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      Mounted cadets in fatigue uniforms with campaign hats. Circa 1917 uniforms with some cadets wearing ties. The building in the background has a brick facade, possibly Langston Hall or Mechanical Hall. The cavalry units at OAC continued till WWII era.
    - Field artillery column by Waldo Hall, circa 1918; P002:406; 8X10 glass positive (Box 8)
      Glass Positive, Hand Colored. Field artillery unit in transit in front of Waldo Hall. Six horse brace with caissons and limbers. The artillery piece in front of column is a "French" 75mm howitzer. These guns were issued at the end of WWI. Uniforms indicate olive drab style with campaign hats. Good detail of Waldo Hall in background.
  - Glass Lantern Slide Collection, Military training aids, circa 1919
    Collection of glass lantern slides of various military subjects. Glass Lantern Slides 3x4. Used as educational aids in Military and Tactics classes at OAC during WWI and into the 1930s. Sub-series contains glass lantern slides of various subjects, military based content. Many slides are marked in lower left corner with "Signal Corps USA", the US Army logo for the information and photography divisions. Photographs are stock images from World War One in Europe, mostly France where the American Expeditionary Force (AEF) was assigned. The US involvement in WWI, April 1917 through November 1918 is represented in the images. Subjects covered in series include engineering, bridge building, railroads and trench construction.
    - WWI era French Portland cement factory, Lavocat & Co., circa 1918; P002:074; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Photograph of French Portland cement factory, probably related to engineer training. Lavocat & Co. plant, possibly in Neuchatel, Pas de Calais. This image was probably used for training of OAC Engineering cadets and illustrates one of the sources for building materials available in France during the period.
    - Loading docks of French cement factory, circa 1918; P002:0075; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Loading docks with storage sheds of possibly French cement plant, related to P002:074. This location appears in later images and is noted as St. Sulpice, France.
    - Ground level view of factory in France, WWI era, circa 1918; P002:076; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Ground level view of main cement plant in France. Probably related to P002:074 of the Lavocat & Co., WWI Era France.
    - Loading docks with railroad track, Lavocat & Co., circa 1918; P002:077; glass lantern slide (Box 3)